anna look we learned the slice yes but
now i remember that story you told me
about that guy you were playing who was
doing these crazy shots george in clinic
yes yes
his breath and butter the first slice
yeah the slice the first one was like
the side spin
okay he does it all the time it's so
hard to it drives you crazy so we say
if we survive george then we're good so
today i'm gonna teach you how to defend
against those type of shots okay okay
back up here a couple more
come on on it go
here one more
all right here we go last one
last one anna
all right is this what that guy does to
you in practice
my mind i'm more nasty
it's completely unpredictable i put a
little extra funk on there but here's
where here's where a lot of recreational
players i'm out of breath
where a lot of recreational players get
in trouble with these balls is in a few
different ways so number one they try to
predict they try to make predictions of
how the ball is going to behave the
promise of these balls is very
unpredictable also a lot of times at the
recreational level these strokes are
made accidentally so nobody can predict
what's going to happen yeah
the person that hit the ball doesn't
even know what's going to happen
opponent doesn't know what's going to
happen so it's very unpredictable
therefore you shouldn't
you shouldn't try to predict and then
try to figure out what the ball is going
to do afterwards you're going to get
frozen with your feet the thought
process takes too long simply don't
think about it don't try to predict what
the ball is going to do but keep your
feet moving as long as possible and just
keep your eyes on the ball in real time
try to track it in real time so as it's
flying to you and then makes that curve
you track that curve in real time this
is going to give you my feet with your
feet and your eyes
your feet and your eyes the ball's
coming you don't try to predict where
it's going to go
follow it in real time as it goes there
you go with it
but then it usually goes opposite
direction
it does but that's if you're predicting
it then it goes in the opposite
direction if you do it in real time
you follow the ball as it's flying so as
it as it takes a turn you go with the
ball with the power of my mind i
change the direction of the ball so what
you got to do is not worry about
predictions and just go with real time
okay also another reason why a lot of
players
uh have a hard time with these type of
balls is shot selection so they hit way
too hard so they hit too hard when the
ball is low and they usually don't bend
either and when the bracket has to bend
this way when it drops below the level
of the handle and now you hit it hard
you have a very disadvantageous position
on the racquet head and you're going to
hit up on the ball most likely with the
string slightly open and it's very easy
to miss the ball long as a result of it
so what you got to do is remember our
forehand topspin lesson
remember
okay we got to do forehand top spin that
is the solution to any low ball problem
number one thing you got to do is bend
when the ball is low you got to stay low
do this with me do a lunge right here do
a lunge
lower
back knee touching the ground on the low
ball you got to really get like this now
this is physically exhausting and very
very challenging physically but that's
what has to be done you have to be low
when the ball is low and in addition to
that you have to make a vertical
movement of the racquet head you have to
go up with the racket as much as you can
to be able to put top spin on it now
what you're doing with that ball you're
not trying to hit a winner you're not
trying to do anything spectacular you're
just trying to neutralize the ball get
it back in play with a decent amount of
height
and pace and then you try to do better
on the next shot
so let me give you a few more and you
try to do exactly that follow the ball
in real time
you bend super low and you put a lot of
spin on it
go again when the ball is low you stay
low beautiful job ana
here we go
absolutely spectacular you see how easy
that is
okay i'm gonna i'm gonna do that now
here back up
keep tracking keep moving your feet
good
don't get stuck when you're stuck you
can't move anymore keep moving longer
batter on a beautiful job
all right let me see backhand
stay lower back up
okay one thing that's important come on
up real quick
when you get one of these super low
balls
it's not going to be possible to raise
up so it's one of those those instances
where you actually stay low
you understand what i'm saying so you
can't really go up with your legs okay
because you're so low you can't get out
of that position that easily okay so
when the ball looks extremely low
you also have to stay low so basically
it's like this watch you get a super low
backhand
and you go here you just stay down here
also what's interesting about this is
that you can see the pros doing this
when that is the case when you're
extremely low and you're staying low you
can't finish the shot all the way
because the torso rotation gets
interrupted
so you're gonna have a shorter finish as
well
but it doesn't change the fact that
you're still trying to put spin
you're basically trying to stay alive
you're not looking to get fancy trying
to be super aggressive you're trying to
stay alive and that is what has to be
done all right here we go come on
down down
keep tracking the ball longer
go up anna
what are you doing what is that
don't slice do a regular backhand
good
oh my goodness so good anna
now watch
this
come on track it
keep your feet moving you're stuck
don't get stuck keep moving
and i keep moving
batter on them good job all right let me
mix it up forehand and back end okay
back up
oh again
come on regular forehand
good
go up more lift that racket up
good anna
wonderful job
go go go go go
come on
come on anna
better
just keep moving it's that simple keep
watching the ball and keep moving
keep moving keep moving don't get stuck
with your feet keep moving
better
okay i had to get out of the way
go again
last one
give you a crazy one
keep moving all right one more it's
going to be the craziest one i've ever
done here we go
anna
amazing when it comes to the low ball
the most important thing is to stay low
on a low ball also
maybe even more important is to keep
moving because you saw how often you got
stuck
keep moving keep moving you started
studying the ball without moving trying
to predict where it's going and stuff
like that don't worry about predictions
follow the ball in real time and keep
moving the whole time follow the ball
the whole time don't commit to the ball
too early
those two things hurt players the most
because when you're lower you have a
better chance to get the proper angle of
the racket face
and also when you actually hit the ball
make the most top spin that you can with
your forehand and with your backhand
eventually
when we improve the slice a little bit
what we did
in our last lesson we will be able to
slice those balls as well because it's a
lot easier to slice a low ball than to
hit it with a two-handed back end like i
said before so as your slice gets better
maybe a year from now a couple years
from now you will be able to slice those
balls as well
on the forehand
slices unnecessary you can always
because you have more length here you
have only one arm it's very easy to
reach those balls so it's not necessary
to do a forehand slice it is often
something that rec players do it's kind
of a lazy shot
so definitely on the forehand low ball
you try to do topspin as much as you can
on the back end you have a little bit
more options
all right do you feel better about the
low ball next time you play that guy
you're going to be more confident yes
yes all right nice work
good job anna
you